<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Uğurcan Akkök</title>
        <link>/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Uğurcan Akkök</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Uğurcan Akkök</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2019 18:17:20 +0300</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Free and Open Source Software</title>
            <link>/posts/foss/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2019 18:17:20 +0300</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/foss/</guid>
            <description>What is Free Software ? First things first, Free doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean free as in beer, it means free as in freedom.
It is designed to protect user&amp;rsquo;s rights to use it, study it and share it. Richard Stallman, the founder of Free Software Foundation (FSF), states it has four essential points.
Users should be able to
 Run it as they wish Study the source code Modify the source code Share the source code with the changes.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<h1 id="what-is-free-software">What is Free Software ?</h1>

<p>First things first, <em>Free</em> doesn&rsquo;t mean <em>free as in beer</em>, it means <em>free as in freedom</em>.<br />
It is designed to protect user&rsquo;s rights to use it, study it and share it.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Stallman">Richard Stallman</a>, the founder of
<a href="https://fsf.org"><em>Free Software Foundation</em> (FSF)</a>, states it has four essential
points.<br />
Users should be able to</p>

<ul>
<li>Run it as they wish</li>
<li>Study the source code</li>
<li>Modify the source code</li>
<li>Share the source code with the changes.</li>
</ul>

<p>Free software is an ethical movement, the idea behind it is to protect people&rsquo;s and humanity&rsquo;s rights about the software.
It has been actively supported by countless of volunteers from all over the world. All has the ethical ideals to defend
human rights without personal profit.</p>

<h2 id="fsf">FSF</h2>

<p>FSF is the leading foundation of the movement. They are actively working on the issue for over 30 years. It all started with
<a href="https://gnu.org">GNU</a> project that is initialized in 1984 by Richard Stallman to enable people to use free software.
By that time, almost all software was proprietary (meaning non-free) and people had to use non-free software. Since then FSF
has the greatest effort on freedom of users and created great projects which are mostly grouped under GNU.</p>

<h2 id="projects">Projects</h2>

<p>There are lots of free software projects for different purposes, and almost all proprietary software has a free
counter-part. Some of the best projects, beside from GNU,in my opinion includes:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blender.org"><strong>Blender</strong></a>
A professional 3D rendering software that has great community support and active development.</li>
<li><a href="https://gimp.org"><strong>GIMP</strong></a>
Image editing software that is able to do most of the things you would expect from Adobe Photoshop.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.videolan.org/vlc"><strong>VLC</strong></a>
I don&rsquo;t see any other multi-media player software that can beat VLC in functionality.</li>
<li><a href="https://vim.org"><strong>Vim</strong></a>
Highly configurable and extensive programmer&rsquo;s text editor.</li>
<li><a href="https://libreoffice.org"><strong>LibreOffice</strong></a>
FOSS office suit, great community support and it does not miss any feature you would need.</li>
<li><a href="https://bitcoincore.org/"><strong>Bitcoin Core</strong></a>
The underlying system under the bitcoin cryptocurrency.</li>
</ul>

<p>It is amazing how much FOSS achieves. Even though those projects are completely free in any means, the maintainers and the
contributors, without focusing on profit, spend their precious time building it.</p>

<h1 id="what-is-open-source-software">What is Open Source Software ?</h1>

<p>Open source is a method for writing the software. It means source code is open to public. So that anyone can contribute to
the project. Anyone can study the code.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it may not be the case that because you are able to see the source code you are
free to modify or share it. License might restrict you from doing so. However most open source projects are considered
free software, so you are free to do most of the things you would want.</p>

<h1 id="the-differences">The Differences</h1>

<p>The differences between Open Source Software and Free Software comes from the idea behind it. The companies that does not
care about user&rsquo;s freedom might still make their project open source because they want people to help them. But the idea
behind Free Software is to respect user&rsquo;s freedom, not just getting help.</p>

<h1 id="why-free-open-source-software">Why Free/Open Source Software ?</h1>

<h2 id="why-i-choose-free-software">Why I Choose Free Software ?</h2>

<p>As a student, I am focused on learning as much as I can. The more resources are available, the better a passionate student can learn.</p>

<p>Being able to see how any software written is a great benefit. That is one of the most efficient ways to learn programming.
Seeing how others (who most probably has more experience than you) wrote it and trying to understand it is essential for a student.</p>

<p>If anyone wants to learn programming, I think the best way is to read and write code. To exercise and observe the others. How else
could you learn anything?</p>

<p>One example for reading other&rsquo;s code would be, if I want to learn a library, I can
go and search for projects who used it and learn from it. Or maybe I want to learn how can I write an emulator for a device, I can study
how others wrote it in the past and build my knowledge upon it.</p>

<p>After reading the source code of a project, if I feel confident enough I would want to make changes either for testing myself or
for adding a functionality I want. And if my friends wants the same functionality I would share it. If I think the project itself might benefit
from the changes i made, such a great thing it would be to make a contribution.</p>

<p>And also I would want as many people as possible to comment on my code so that I can improve it. Which is very useful for
a student.</p>

<p>Since I demand such rights, it is only rightful if I want other people to have the same rights. Also, for a better software world,
those rights are essential. They allow people to learn and share so that they will be better programmers. And the end product can
benefit everyone.</p>

<h2 id="why-you-should-choose-free-open-source-software">Why You Should Choose Free/Open Source Software ?</h2>

<p>First, if you agree with the above part, you probably already want to choose free/open source software.</p>

<p>As a user, even if you are not a programmer, you should choose FOSS because this way, developers of the program you use
can not do anything illegal or that you don&rsquo;t want. For example Windows is known for forcing people to update the system,
even if the user explicitly chose not to do so. It is known that Microsoft has placed a backdoor in the Windows. And lets
not forget about all the surveillance that is happening. Even if you don&rsquo;t care about surveillance, you probably care about
the speed, responsiveness and effectiveness of the software you use. If program spends the resources on spying on you,
it can not be efficient as much.</p>

<p>As a programmer, you might get and will probably get help from the community. It can be a translation help, documentation
or some code changes. Also the people that want to work with you will regularly contribute to your project, you can hire them.
Most importantly, you will help the community by sharing the code.Returning the favor to the community is a must especially if you are
a self-learner who has learned much from the community.
If you are in a big company, don&rsquo;t forget that there are thousands of companies which use Open Source Licenses. For example
Mozilla is a giant company that uses open source in every project, Android is an open source project which Google owns.
<a href="https://www.redhat.com/">Red Hat Linux</a>, which is recently owned by IBM, is an open source project that you can use
for free but if you buy it, they also give technical support with the other things like courses.</p>

<p>Beside do not forget that if you use an open source program/library in your project, depends on that project&rsquo;s license, you
might have to make your project open source.</p>

<h1 id="which-licenses-to-use">Which Licenses to Use ?</h1>

<p>The FSF suggests you to use <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.en.html">GNU General Public License</a> if you want people to use
FOSS licenses too.  If you do not care about the license of the project that your software used in, you can use
<a href="https://opensource.org/licenses/MIT">MIT License</a>. It is as permissive as possible.</p>

<p>For a more comprehensive suggestions, see <a href="https://choosealicense.com/">Choosing a License</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
